Pablo Catalán Fernández

PhD student Grupo Interdisciplinar de Sistemas Complejos (GISC) Department of Mathematics Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (UC3M) Avenida de la Universidad 30 28911 Leganés (SPAIN)

Career summary

I am doing my PhD in theoretical evolutionary biology under the supervision of Professor José A. Cuesta. We are interested in understanding the complexities of the genotype-phenotype map and their consequences on the dynamics of the evolutionary process. To this end, we have developed toyLIFE, a computational model that integrates molecular, regulatory and metabolic processes, and that will allow us to study the construction and evolution of complex phenotypes.

Telephone: 0034 645 553 887

Email: pcatalan@math.uc3m.es Website: UC3M Personal Website

Education

Sep 2013—present: BSc in Mathematics (4-year degree, currently studying 4th year) Universidad Española de Educación a Distancia (UNED)

Sep 2011—Oct 2012: MSc in Modelling and Physics of Complex Systems

Universidad Rey Juan Carlos I de Madrid (URJC)

GPA: 3.45 || Thesis: Mutation-selection equilibrium in finite populations playing a Hawk-Dove game

Sep 2006—Jun 2011: BSc+MSc in Biology (5-year degree)

Universidad Complutense de Madrid (UCM)

GPA: 3.66 (Graduated with honors)

Additional formation

Sept 2013 Third Summer School on Physics of Complex and Small Systems Organized by GEFENOL and IFISC

Awards

Mar 2016 MINECO Short-Term Fellowship: 60 days visit to Robert Beardmore's lab, University of Exeter.

Mar 2015 EMBO Short-Term Fellowship: 90 days visit to Andreas Wagner's lab, University of Zurich.

Professional Experience

Dec 2012—present: Predoctoral fellow (FPI fellowship)

Department of Mathematics, Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (UC3M)

Research topic: Models in molecular evolution

Supervisor: Prof. José A. Cuesta

Oct 2010—Jun 2011: Assistant scholar

Department of Ecology, Universidad Complutense de Madrid (UCM) Research topic: Reproductive allocation strategies in *Cistus ladanifer*

Supervisor: Dr. Juan Antonio Delgado

Jun 2010—Sep 2010: Research assistant

Department of Ecosystem Biogeochemistry, Institute of Natural Resources (CSIC)

Research topic: Biogeochemistry in lakes Supervisor: Prof. Salvador Sánchez-Carrillo

Dec 2008—Jun 2010: Excellency scholar

Department of Ecology, Universidad Complutense de Madrid (UCM) Research topic: Reproductive allocation strategies in *Cistus ladanifer*

Supervisor: Dr. Juan Antonio Delgado

Languages

English: Full professional proficiency (C2).

French: Elementary proficiency (A2).

Publications

- 7. Catalán, P., Arias, C.F., Cuesta, J. A. and Manrubia, S. **2017** Adaptive multiscapes: an up-to-date metaphor to visualize molecular adaptation. *Biology Direct* **12:7**.
- 6. Catalán, P., Delgado, J.A., Jiménez, M.D. and Balaguer, L. **2016**. Sink strength manipulation in branches of a Mediterranean woody plant suggests sink-driven allocation of biomass in fruits but not of nutrients in seeds. *Acta Physiologiae Plantarum* **38:193**.
- 5. Planchuelo, G., <u>Catalán</u>, P. and Delgado, J.A. **2016**. Gone with the wind and the stream: Dispersal in the invasive species *Ailanthus altissima*. *Acta Oecologica* **73:31-37**.
- Planchuelo, G., <u>Catalán, P.</u>, Delgado, J.A. and Murciano A. 2016. Estimating wind dispersal potential in *Ailanthus altissima*: The need to consider the three-dimensional structure of samaras. *Plant Biosystems*, DOI: 10.1080/11263504.2016.1174170.
- 3. Catalán, P., Seoane, J.M. and Sanjuán, M.A.F. **2015**. Mutation-selection equilibrium in finite populations playing a Hawk-Dove game. *Communications in Nonlinear Science and Numerical Simulations* **25:66-73**.
- 2. Arias, C.F., <u>Catalán, P.</u>, Manrubia, S.M. and Cuesta, J.A. **2014**. toy LIFE: a computational framework to study the multi-level organization of the genotype-phenotype map. *Scientific Reports* **4**: **7549**.
- 1. Catalán, P., Vázquez de Aldana, B.R., De las Heras, P., Fernández-Seral, A. and Pérez-Corona, M.E. 2013. Comparing the allelopathic potential of exotic and native plant species on understory plants: are exotic plants better armed? *Anales de Biología* 35: 65-74.

Conference contributions

Posters

- 4. Catalán, P., Fernández-Arias, C. and Cuesta, J. A. 2014. toyLIFE: un universo de juguete para comprender mejor la evolución. XIX Congreso de Física Estadística (FISES '14). April 2-4th 2014, Ourense (Spain).
- 3. Catalán, P., Jiménez, M.D., Delgado, J.A. and Balaguer, L. 2011. Variation in sink strength affects size-mediated competition within the crown. 12 th EEF Congress. September 25-29th 2011, Ávila (Spain).

- 2. Pérez-Corona, M.E., Catalán, P., Fernández-Seral, A., De las Heras, P., Castro-Díez, P. and Vázquez de Aldana, B.R. 2011. Effect of riverine invasive species in germination and radicle growth of understory species. 12 th EEF Congress. September 25-29th 2011, Ávila (Spain).
- 1. Pérez-Borrero, B., Catalán, P., Aguilar, E.Y., Fontecha, G., Trabanino, R., Gallego, F.J., Figueiras, A.M. and Benito, C. 2010. Identificación con diferentes marcadores moleculares de cepas de Beauveria bassiana utilizadas en la lucha biológica contra la broca del café (Hypothenemus hampei). XII Congreso Internacional de manejo integrado de plagas / XX reunión anual de la Sociedad americana de fitopatología (APS-CD). August 24-27th 2010, Managua (Nicaragua).

Talks

- 4. Catalán, P. 2016. toy LIFE, or the importance of being promiscuous. International Workshop on Genotype-Phenotype Maps 2016 (IWGP 2016). 8-9 September 2016, Cambridge (UK) (invited talk).
- 3. Catalán, P. 2015. toy LIFE: the complexities of the genotype-phenotype map. Modelling Biological Evolution 2015 (MBE '15), April 28-May 1 2015, Leicester (UK) (invited talk).
- 2. Catalán, P. 2014. toyllFE: a toy Universe for gaining insight into biological evolution. XI GISC Workshop, February 7th 2014, Madrid (Spain).
- 1. Catalán, P., Fernández-Arias, C. and Cuesta, J. A. 2013. toyLlFE: a toy Universe for gaining insight into evolution. 4th SESBE Meeting. November 27-29th 2013, Barcelona (Spain).